"Fenugreek Benefits for Sexual Function,
Painful Periods, and Milk Production"
In my video, the "Benefits of
Fenugreek Seeds," I profiled this study
in which young men were randomized
to a sugar pill or fenugreek capsules
for eight weeks and got a significant
improvement in upper body strength,
lower body strength,
and body composition,
a significant reduction
in body fat percentage.
And the only side effect?
It can make your sweat and
pee smell like maple syrup.
Seems like a bonus!
Studies on immature castrated rats
suggest the fenugreek muscle
bulking is a testosterone effect,
but we didn't know what
happens in humans...until now.
Four randomized controlled
trials put it to the test and
saw a significant boost
of total blood testosterone.
And indeed, fenugreek appears
to improve sexual function in men,
for example, doubling the
frequency of morning erections.
What about the sexual function
in women? While the estrogen
hormone, estradiol, stimulates
vaginal lubrication and blood flow,
facilitating a woman's capacity
for sexual arousal and orgasm,
it's the testosterone that's
linked with sexual desire
in both men and women.
Drug companies have tried
testosterone patches on women
to try to increase sexual desire,
but we're concerned
about blood clots
and long-term safety.
What about a little fenugreek?
A significant increase in
testosterone compared to placebo
and a boost in the estrogen estradiol,
which resulted in both an increase
in sexual desire and function,
translating into about a doubling
of sexual activity
compared to placebo.
If fenugreek causes an increase
in estrogen levels, what about
the efficacy of fenugreek for
reducing menopausal symptoms?
A significant reduction in menopausal
symptoms across every single domain,
for example, cutting the weekly
numbers of hot flashes and
night sweats in half over
a period of three months.
Other hormonal effects include
an improvement in painful periods.
What I like about this study is that
they didn't use some propriety extract,
but just straight, plain fenugreek
powder that you'd buy at the store.
Now, they packed it into capsules
just so they could pit it against
a sugar pill placebo,
but the dose they used
is just about a third of
a teaspoon three times a day,
taken the first three
days of their period.
A third of a teaspoon would
cost less than 5 cents.
And boom!
A significant decrease in pain,
and also appeared to improve
other symptoms as well.
While we're on a roll with hormonal
effects, what about the effectiveness
of fenugreek as a galactagogue?
No, not another sci-fi reboot.
A galactagogue is something that
increases breast milk production
in lactating mothers, and
fenugreek fits the bill.
And not just by a little.
In this randomized double-blind
placebo-controlled trial in which
breastfeeding women took less
than a quarter teaspoon of fenugreek,
less than a quarter teaspoon
of ground ginger,
and about a 16th of a teaspoon
of turmeric every day,
doubled their milk production
within a month,
about a 50% increase by week two
and a 100% increase by week four.
However, due to its potential
stimulation on the uterus,
fenugreek seeds should not
be used during pregnancy.
Though this is all based
on laboratory animal data,
better safe than sorry.